Konvitz, Milton R. Papers /4039
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Konvitz - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1969-1983 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Konvitz - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1969-1983 (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Konvitz - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1969-1983 (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Konvitz - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1969-1983 (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Konvitz - Editorials, 1955-1973 (Box 23, Folder 17)
    Correspondence regarding editorials about Liberia, Cornell United Religious Works, and letter to editor urging New Yorkers to vote for Jack B. Weinstein as Chief Judge of the Court of Appeals
  - Konvitz - Kaplun Prize, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 18)
    Letters of congratulations to Konvitz on his being the recipient of the Morris J. Kaplun International Prize for distinguished research and scholarship established at the Hebrew University in Jerusalem; newspaper clipping; program; Konvitz's speech during the presentation.
  - Aber, Rabbi Felix - Ordination (Fortieth Anniversary) (Box 23, Folder 19)
  - American Ideals Course, Last Lecture, 1974 (Box 23, Folder 20)
    December 1974
  - Are Professors Afraid? (Box 23, Folder 21)
  - Berlin Crisis (Box 23, Folder 22)
  - Bible and Hebrew Studies Return to Cornell (Box 23, Folder 23)
  - B'nai B'rith Hillel - Twenty-fifth Celebration (Cornell University) (Box 23, Folder 24)
  - Brandeis (Box 23, Folder 25)
  - Brandeis Centennial Medal to Cornell University, Presentation of (Box 23, Folder 26)
  - Bill of Rights (Box 23, Folder 27)
  - Communist Threat to Underdeveloped Countries (Box 23, Folder 28)
  - Compatibility of Organization and Freedom in Jewish Education (Box 23, Folder 29)
  - Constitution and Civil Rights Demonstrations (Box 23, Folder 30)
  - Cornell University Class of 1958 - Guest Speaker (Box 23, Folder 31)
  - Corporations - Unions (National Broadcasting Company) (Box 23, Folder 32)
  - The Crisis of Civil Liberties and the Moral Judgment (Box 23, Folder 33)
  - Current Problems in Labor Relations and Arbitration (Box 23, Folder 34)
  - Daiches - Debate (Box 23, Folder 35)
  - Does the Press Hamper Fair Trials (Box 23, Folder 36)
  - The Founding of the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations (Box 23, Folder 37)
  - Freedom (Box 23, Folder 38)
  - Goldfarb, Morris Rabbi - Celebration - Tribute (Box 23, Folder 39)
  - Goodman, Paul - Introduction of (Cornell United Religious Works) (Box 23, Folder 40)
  - How Can Man Know God (Box 23, Folder 41)
  - International Orientation Conference for Foreign and American Students (Box 23, Folder 42)
  - Israel (Box 23, Folder 43)
  - Israel Night (Box 23, Folder 44)
  - Israel Rally - Cornell University (Box 23, Folder 45)
  - Ithaca Tercentenary Celebration (Box 23, Folder 46)
  - Jewish Community of Essex County (Box 23, Folder 47)
  - Jewish Education - Crucial Issues (Box 23, Folder 48)
  - Jewish Ethics and American Law (Box 23, Folder 49)
  - Jewish Intellectual, the University, the Jewish Community (Box 23, Folder 50)
  - Judaism (Box 23, Folder 51)
  - Judaism and American Ideals (Box 23, Folder 52)
  - Judaism and the Pursuit of Happiness (Box 23, Folder 53)
  - Kallen, H.M. (Box 23, Folder 54)
  - Kallen, Horace M., The Jewishness of (Box 23, Folder 55)
  - Kallen, Horace M. - Ninetieth Birthday (Box 23, Folder 56)
  - Kennedy, John F. - Memorial Service (Box 23, Folder 57)
  - Klal Yisroel: The Broadening of an Ideal (Box 23, Folder 58)
  - Lady Chatterley's Lover (Box 23, Folder 59)
  - Literature is Where You Find It (Box 23, Folder 60)
  - My Brother Ben-Zion (Box 23, Folder 61)
  - New York University Alumni (Box 23, Folder 62)
  - The Nature of Bronson Alcott (Box 23, Folder 63)
  - On the Limits of Cornell United religious Works (Box 23, Folder 64)
  - Our Basic American Ideals (Box 23, Folder 65)
  - The Persistent Question to the Jew: Who Are You? (Box 23, Folder 66)
  - Privacy and the College Student (Box 23, Folder 67)
  - Religion and the Election (Box 23, Folder 68)
  - Science (Box 23, Folder 69)
  - Science and National Policy (Box 23, Folder 70)
  - Silent March of Mourning (Box 23, Folder 71)
  - Some Subversive Thoughts About Education at Cornell (Box 23, Folder 72)
  - Son of Man, Stand Upon Your Feet (Box 23, Folder 73)
  - The Student and Civil Rights (Box 23, Folder 74)
  - State University of New York Faculty Assembly (Box 23, Folder 75)
  - The Student's Right to Be Let Alone (Box 23, Folder 76)
  - Thomas, Norman - Introduction of (Box 23, Folder 77)
  - Thorp Lectures (Introducing Carl Michalson) (Box 23, Folder 78)
  - Ware Lecture (Box 23, Folder 79)
  - Weinberg Seminar (Box 23, Folder 80)
  - What About Learning to Be A Good Citizen; Yavits, Isadore (Dinner) (Box 23, Folder 81)
  - Zionism: Homecoming or Homelessness? (Box 23, Folder 82)
  - Konvitz - Speeches, Addresses, Lectures, Notes (Continued). Miscellaneous - Untitled (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Krantz, Irwin - Personal Correspondence between Konvitz and Former Student, 1948-1953 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Krock, Arthur (New York Times), 1949 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    Includes 5 page letter by Konvitz regarding his views on Hiss Trial, Judge Kaufman, and the lawyers involved.
  - L- General, 1947-1959 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    Correspondence from Val Lorwin and letter from Konvitz to Attorney Herbert Brownell, Junior, regarding the Lorwin Case (1954) plus routine and personal correspondence.
  - LA-LE - General, 1960-1989 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    Literary, routine, and personal correspondence including letter of September 12, 1989 by Corliss Lamont on John Dewey.
  - Labor Library (Ernest Solit, Director of Sales and Promotion), 1951 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    Konvitz was a member of advisory panel; routine correspondence
  - Lall, Betty G., 1975-1976 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    Includes draft copy by Lall, "Organized Labor's Community Work," 46 pages; also "Impact of National Health Insurance on Union Health Plans," 55 pages; "Union Health Centers of New York City," 32 pages; and unrelated memorandums
  - Lampert, Bernard P., former student, 1947-1956 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Law and Contemporary Problems (Duke University, School of Law), 1949-1955 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    Correspondence regarding Konvitz's contributions to the publication
  - Law and Society Association - Routine Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Law Students Civil Rights Research Council (New York), 1969-1976 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    Konvitz was faculty advisor to Council; includes program, by-laws, publication, correspondence, etcetera
  - League for Industrial Democracy - Routine Correspondence and Publications, 1950-1980 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Lee, Alfred McClung (Brooklyn College, Department of Sociology) - Routine and literary correspondence, 1947-1954 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Leon, Donald E., 1967 (Box 24, Folder 14)
    File on dismissal of Leon from Cortland State College
  - Lerner, Earle, former student, 1948-1951 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Leskes, Theodore (with American Jewish Committee) - literary and personal correspondence, 1958-1963 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Lett, Harold A., New Jersey Department of Education - Personal, 1947-1968 (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Levin, A. Leo (editor, Horizon), 1944-1953 (Box 24, Folder 18)
    Letter from doctor Konvitz (December 1950) giving his views on separation of church and state and routine literary correspondence
  - Levinthal, Louis E. (Judge) - Routine correspondence, 1949-1963 (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Levitas, Sol (editor, New Leader) - Routine literary correspondence, 1947-1961 (Box 24, Folder 20)
  - Levitats, Isaac, Executive Director of the Bureau of Jewish Education - Correspondence on Jewish educational issues in the Syracuse community, 1949 (Box 24, Folder 21)
  - Levitsky, Louis M., Rabbi - Personal correspondence, 1949-1975 (Box 24, Folder 22)
  - Levy, Beryl - Personal Correspondence, 1947-1980 (Box 24, Folder 23)
  - Lewis, Walter and Ethylene - Personal Correspondence, 1950-1959 (Box 24, Folder 24)
    Mrs. Lewis was Professor Konvitz's former secretary, Mr. Lewis, former student.
  - LF-LZ General Correspondence, 1964-1980 (Box 24, Folder 25)
    Correspondence with Sol M. Linowitz regarding problems of obtaining competent teachers for a constitutional justice course which Linowitz suggested in an editorial in the Times and routine; with Val Lorwin regarding Konvitz's feelings about "the world and our country" (February 8, 1968) and personal; and other personal and routine.
  - Liberian Codification - Firestone Company, 1965-1975 (Box 24, Folder 26)
    Correspondence with officials of Firestone Plantations Company on an Industrial Relations Conference in Liberia on the labor situation in Liberia, and on various aspects of the Labor Code (Company has office in Liberia)
  - Liberian Codification - Finance Statements, 1968-1975 (Box 24, Folder 27)
    Project financial statements from finance and business office, Cornell University
  - Liberian Codification - Koss, Milton (research associate with Project), 1969-1973 (Box 24, Folder 28)
    Correspondence with Koss, project staff in New York City, regarding various drafts of code: proof reading, correcting, etcetera
  - Liberian Codification - Liberian Mining Company - Routine Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 24, Folder 29)
  - Liberian Codification Project (Peace Corps, Liberia) - Relative to sending American lawyers to Liberia as a Peace Corps Project, 1962- 1967 (Box 24, Folder 30)
  - Liberian Codification Project - Pierre, James, Chief Justice of Liberia, 1971-1974 (Box 24, Folder 31)
    Correspondence regarding the Project; and personal, 8 page "Tribute to Late President Tubman (Liberia) by Chief Justice Pierre"; also "Address delivered by His Honor James A.A. Pierre, Chief Justice of Liberia on the occasion of the First Judicial Conference of Liberia," in which he discusses Professor Konvitz's project; financial problems regarding the project
  - Liberian Codification Project - Rosenzweig, Margaret, Director of Research (New York City) for the Project - Routine Project Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Liberian Codification Project - Simpson, Clarence, Minister of Justice - Routine Correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Liberian Codification Project - Routine Correspondence, 1963-1980 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Liberian Codification Project - Routine Correspondence, 1963-1980 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Liberian Codification Project - Routine Correspondence, 1963-1980 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Liberian Codification Project - School (New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations News) - Routine memorandums regarding office space, budget, staff, etcetera, 1966-1976 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Lilly, Warren C. - Correspondence between Lilly and Konvitz on religion in public schools and religion in general, 1947-1949 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Lincoln University - Correspondence regarding the offer of presidency of Lincoln University to Doctor Konvitz, 1959-1961 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Linowitz, sol M. (Attorney, Rochester, New York) - Routine Correspondence, 1958-1966 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Locke, Alain (Howard University) - Personal Correspondence, 1958-1966 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Lown, Philip - Personal Correspondence, 1965-1977 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - M - General Correspondence, 1947-1959 (Box 25, Folder 12)
    Substantial correspondence between Konvitz and J.B. Matthews (New York City) (1953) on the alleged involvement of Professor Horace Kallen with Communist organizations. Also literary and personal correspondence.
  - M - General Correspondence, 1960-1980 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    Substantial amount of correspondence with Representative Matthew F. McHugh relative to his thoughts on Israel situation, his election, and legislation
  - M - General Correspondence, 1960-1980 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - Magen David Adom Society (Konvitz was a member of the National Committee) - Correspondence and Newsletters, 1975-1976 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Marrow, Alfred J. (President, American Board of Professional Psychology, Incorporated), 1948-1978 (Box 25, Folder 16)
    Personal correspondence regarding Horace Kallen and plans honoring Kallen's retirement; plans for Kallen's birthday parties; editing of Kallen's book by Marrow; appeals for special H. Kallen Fund at the New School and other personal
  - Marshall, Thurgood (United States Supreme Court), 1961-1967 (Box 25, Folder 17)
    Letters of congratulation from Doctor Konvitz; three page letter from Konvitz refreshing Thurgood's recollection about Konvitz's Liberian Codification Project before he leaves to make a speech at the inauguration of President Tubman in Liberia
  - Maslow, Will (Director, American Jewish Congress), 1946-1976 (Box 25, Folder 18)
    Literary, legal, and personal correspondence; copies of 1949 and 1950 minutes of the american Jewish Congress Commission on Law and Social Action; January 26, 1948 letter asking Konvitz if he knows whether the War Department has been pushing Nazi scientists into American Universities, including Cornell University, and Doctor Konvitz's reply.
  - McPhelin, Michael (Professor, Cornell University Department of Economics), 1968-1969 (Box 25, Folder 19)
    Copies of memorandums on McPhelin and tenure; six page memorandum to the Committee on Academic Freedom and Tenure from Professor Richard I. Hofferbert on the present state of academic freedom at Cornell.
  - Memorial Foundation for Jewish Culture, 1976-1980 (Box 25, Folder 20)
    Konvitz, Chairman, Committee on Scholarships and Fellowships. Includes correspondence, reports of the Committee, scattered minutes of Planning Committee.
  - Memorial Foundation for Jewish Culture, 1976-1980 (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - Merrill, Charles E. - Trust - Correspondence regarding grant proposals, 1966-1980 (Box 25, Folder 22)
  - Messenger Lectures - Routine memorandums regarding suggestions for speakers, 1946-1953 (Box 25, Folder 23)
  - Meyer, Julie (Professor, New School for Social Research) - Routine correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 25, Folder 24)
  - Midstream, 1957-1981 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    Professor Konvitz served on the editorial board. Includes correspondence on formation of a Midstream faculty group at Cornell; internal problems; minutes of the editorial board; eight page "Tribute to Emanuel Neumann on Publication of His Autobiography" by Konvitz; comments and observations of Midstream articles by Konvitz; considerable amount of general correspondence relative to the internal operations of the editorial board: decisions on articles for publication, book reviews, etcetera.
  - Midstream, 1957-1981 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Midstream, 1957-1981 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Milgram, Morris (Director, Workers Defense League; President, Modern Community Developers, Incorporated) - Personal correspondence, 1946- 1966 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Milton, John - Personal correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Minkoff, Nahum B. - Personal, literary correspondence, 1947-1956 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    Most of the materials are in Yiddish
  - Mohawk Airlines (Dispute) - routine correspondence regarding arbitration hearing arrangements, 1963-1966 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Mishnun, Virginia - Personal correspondence, 1949-1954 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Morris, William (Society) - routine literary, 1961-1962 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Morrow, Felix (Vice President, Schocken Books, Incorporated) - routine literary correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Moskowitz, David - Personal Correspondence, 1948-1974 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Muste, A.J. - Chairman, Committee for Amnesty; Secretary, Fellowship of Reconciliation; Executive Committee, War Resistors League, 1946- 1955 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    Letter thanking Professor Konvitz for a copy of his book (1946); December 27, 1946 letter regarding amnesty for conscientious objectors in prisons including Jehovah's Witnesses; letter to Doctor Albert Einstein, September 15, 1947, from Muste regarding atomic war threat; regarding militarization in the United States; also requests for various financial contributions.
  - Myers, Henry A. (Late Cornell University professor) - personal correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - N - General, 1946-1980 (Box 26, Folder 14)
    With Professor Ernest Nagel, Columbia University concerning New Leader article by Konvitz regarding Communism and other routine (1946-1954); Herbert R. Northrup relative to a critical review of Northrup's book by an Industrial and Labor Relations professor and routine literary (1946-1953); fifteen page address by Vernon E. Jordan, Junior, President, National Urban League, Incorporated, given at annual meeting, National Conference of Catholic Charities, 1979; and other personal and literary items.
  - N - General, 1946-1980 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - Nathanson, Jerome - Chairman, Committee on Federal Aid to Public Education, with Society for Ethical Culture in the City of New York - Correspondence regarding John Dewey; federal aid to education, personal, and routine correspondence., 1944-1955 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1947-1979 (Box 26, Folder 17)
    Konvitz was a member of the Legal Committee. Correspondence with Walter White, Secretary of the National Association for the Advancement of colored People, and other officials regarding the establishment of an International Court of Human rights; relative to George Schuyler who, it was alleged, deliberately falsified facts regarding the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People; with Thurgood Marshall, Special Counsel, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People regarding the South Carolina Democratic Party (1948) excluding blacks; discrimination in the National Guard, dining cars; with W.E.B. DuBois, Director, Department of Special Research with relation to the legal status of the Negroes; report to the United Nations on the rights of American Negroes; with Roy Wilkins, Executive Secretary relative to his speaking engagement at Cornell University and other routine issues; with Jack Greenberg, Director Counsel, Legal Defense and Education Fund, Incorporated, regarding sit-in cases before the Supreme Court as well as other cases.
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1947-1979 (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - National Association of Intergroup Relations Officials - Routine conference materials, 1949-1953 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - National Citizen's Council on Civil Rights - Correspondence and statements in relation to setting up a permanent Federal Commission of Civil Rights, 1948-1949 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - National Community Relations Advisory Council (Konvitz, member) - Includes reports, statements, other publications and some routine correspondence., 1949-1979 (Box 26, Folder 21)
  - National Community Relations Advisory Council (Konvitz, member) - Includes reports, statements, other publications and some routine correspondence., 1949-1979 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews - Doctor Konvitz was a member, Commission on Community Organizations, Committee on Educational Organizations. Includes publications and routine organizational correspondence., 1946-1978 (Box 26, Folder 23)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews - Doctor Konvitz was a member, Commission on Community Organizations, Committee on Educational Organizations. Includes publications and routine organizational correspondence., 1946-1978 (Box 26, Folder 24)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) - Correspondence and completed forms, reviews of grant proposals by Konvitz to the National Endowment for the Humanities, 1977-1980 (Box 26, Folder 25)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) - Correspondence and completed forms, reviews of grant proposals by Konvitz to the National Endowment for the Humanities, 1977-1980 (Box 26, Folder 26)
  - National Enforcement Commission (Economic Stabilization Agency - Professor Konvitz was on the staff of the enforcement commissioners to hear cases in the Rochester-Syracuse area) - Routine Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - National Foundation for Jewish Culture (Konvitz was a member of the Academic Advisory Council) - Includes routine correspondence and agendas for meetings, 1976-1980 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  - National Urban League (Konvitz was a member of the National Committee) - Correspondence regarding setting up a branch of the National League in Ithaca; also routine correspondence., 1946-1959 (Box 26, Folder 29)
  - Neumann, Emanuel - Chairman of the United States section of the World Zionist Organization. Personal Correspondence., 1949- 1979 (Box 26, Folder 30)
  - New Jersey Department of Education - Division Against Discrimination, 1956-1960 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    Includes reports by Konvitz and others relative to the compliance operations of the agency with suggestions and recommendations for improvement; publications and correspondence regarding the report.
  - The New Leader (Miscellaneous, Personal, Literary Correspondence), 1958-1966 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - New School for Social Research - Correspondence about fund raising for the Kallen Chair and routine, 1959-1977 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - New York State - Miscellaneous Albany Correspondence relative to legislative bills pertaining to obscenity, 1962-1963 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - New York State Labor Relations Board (Honorable Joseph DiFede, Chairman) - Correspondence regarding arrangements for DiFede's visits to Cornell University as a visiting lecturer., 1955-1960 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - New York Times - Letters to the editor, 1946-1965 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    Topics covered include Palestine, the United Nations, an anti-lynching bill, American-Israel relations, exploiting Arab refugees, birth control, and civil rights.
  - New York Times - Editorials, 1956-1957 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    Correspondence relative to Doctor Konvitz's letters to the editor on Arab refugees and other subjects
  - New York University Award, 1964-1969 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    Clippings, program, correspondence about the Alumni Achievement award presented to Konvitz by Washington Square College Alumni Association of New York University (1964)
  - Newport (Rhode Island) Religious Freedom Conference, 1978 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    Konvitz was a participant in the Symposium, "From Religious Toleration to Religious Freedom." Includes correspondence and 20 page speech given by Konvitz.
  - Night call Radio Program - regarding Konvitz's appearance on the program, 1969 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Nixon, Richard M. - Vice President, 1957-1958 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    Letter inviting Doctor Konvitz to Conference of Presidential Committee on Government Contracts; and other expressing his appreciation for attending Minority Community Resources Conference.
  - Norman, Dorothy - Editor of Twice a Year. Literary Correspondence., 1946-1948 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - O - General Correspondence, 1947-1980 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    Correspondence between Konvitz and Victor A. Olander, Secretary-Treasurer, Illinois State Federation of Labor (1947) on the civil rights of labor; with Donald Otis relative to the editing and publication of the Horace Kallen anthology; a letter to John M. Olin from Professor Konvitz (1961) thanking Olin for the funding for the John M. Olin Library and Olin's reply.
  - O - General Correspondence, 1947-1980 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Oko, Dorothy - Correspondence relative to Horace Kallen Fund fundraising efforts and personal, 1947-1971 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - Orlinsky, Harry M. (Hebrew Union College) - Personal Correspondence, 1956-1979 (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Out of State and Foreign - routine and literary correspondence, 1953-1965 (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - Out of State and Foreign - Routine and Literary Correspondence, 1953-1965 (Box 27, Folder 18)